all right welcome
back it's March 4th the only day that's
a command March 4th so as we head into
chapter 3 does anyone want to begin with
any any thoughts or questions or remarks
about
three or where is it in the context of
the
book what do they remember from it or
what's a quote that was interesting or
just a point to jump in from
I personally found it really interesting
that the marov blanket is just an
intermediary it's just a barrier between
two things the external and the internal
State I really it reminded me of my
physics classes talking about a ball
rolling down the hill in the sense that
you could take it from the perspective
of the ball and the universe of moving
around it or the the universe is still
and the ball is moving down the hill
that freedom for that kind of reference
surprised
me yeah interesting stable Hill moving
ball and stable Ball moving
Hill that that is that it
Zach absolutely yeah yeah
that a kind of similar topic came up
yesterday in the um discussion with llan
Kent and Anna Unica on mental gravity on
like kind of there's a reference frame
where the Earth like spaceship earth is
the egocentric navigation that's like
our visual reality like objects coming
closer and then there's kind of a third
person Sun centrism there's other
reference points that can be chosen but
that's definitely a very
so how would you connect that to markup
blanket or to
AC or how does the Markov blanket allow
us to to do it this
way wait I'm sorry perhaps I don't
understand are you saying they posed
that question or are you asking that
question oh just asking like what what
made you what made you think about this
ball moving down the hill from the
markof blanket
oh because of the K Divergence it's not
exactly perfect but it seems as if you
uh can
move X the actual like external world is
going to stay still but the Q is going
to be the thing that's
changing however it seems to where your
choice as the ball as the thing moving
down the hill is kind of arbitrary if
you assume that the K Divergence is not
going to change if you change up the
order it was just a thought that I had
that found to be interesting the kind of
relative relationship between the two
perhaps there's not much to it well well
I'm I'm seeing
maybe the lrange points as being
somewhat
porary what are those points so when you
have an orbit um when you have two
bodies in orbits there are certain
points where there's an
equilibrium between the gravity Fields
between those two bodies so the lrange
point is actually a place of
stasis um and in a way because it's an
absence of both those bodies and the in
the influence of both those bodies it's
actually a separate virtual body in and
of
itself so or a virtual Point excuse
me that that's very interesting lock Li
in in this kind of mental gravity um
discussion which maybe people can look
at for more detail it's like he did
discuss the center of gravity those
topics came up with the basian mechanics
and Dalton otiva devel like you have a
distribution and then you have a center
of Mass center of gravity that's like
the central tendency of a distribution
so basing mechanics is kind of something
like a gravitational interpretation of
the basian updating process like big
distribution heavy prior Light low
attention uh sensory input not going to
move the prior that much and then the um
lrange point is kind of like the the
stationarity if you're there like a
non-equilibrium stationary
Point like uh the person in the frog and
the uh jumping out of the hand example a
textbook they could reach like a
long-term stationerity where they were
just
estimating something that where they
kind of they've reached like a steady
point with what their environment was
providing so it's kind of like one
Gravity from the environment one Gravity
from the um agent with their prior and
then also that the um p is stable like
the true distribution of uh temperature
stable Q is changing beliefs are
changing or beliefs are stable true
distributions are
changing and that kind of uh maps to
the um change the world change the
Mind
possibility
like belief
updating and fixed belief World State
changing so nice lot of great comments
here
Thomas and then
yeah yeah two points one is I found
really fascinating the Reliance on
temporal dimensionality for a lot of the
argumentation here so for example the
argument of basic the high rical gener
generative model for example the
illustration of sentences right composed
of words uh their high rical orentation
is based on a nature of duration things
are taking longer than other
uh that's a really fat basically things
are taking a rapidity a rapidness of
movement versus a duration longer period
of time um as the argumentation for like
what gives an ordering to things I think
that's incredibly fascinating another
dimension related to this idea of like
emotional like why we're talking about
this kind of psychological aspect of
gravity um there's that line where that
idea of temporal depth is directly
correlated with psychological dep of a
person and that's really interesting on
a couple grounds one is I'm attaching
this that ideas of the kind of factual
and trajectories and policies
argumentation that's been presented so
far AOS has a really fascinating line in
metaphysics about rational action
activity he uses a very particular
example of a rock a rock is IR R the
activity of a rock dropping is not
rational because it has it's compelled
by necessity to have to go down the
point versus rational actions there's
AOS a power of Choice a power of D of
deral of of either to dox or not do X so
the counterfactual point the example use
in Ariz metaphysics is uh medicine right
to heal or not to heal for example um or
that actor basically the agent throwing
the rock or not throwing the rock again
that cap like that the drawing of
rational activity to be that power of
choice of temporal optionality basically
um I saw some correspondence to notes
like that I've always always find that
very interesting AOS style he talks
about that's his def that's like
derivative his explicit definition of
what rational activity is uh which has
this kind of potentiality temporal
nature to it I thought that was really
fascinating um the other note it's a
classic problem um this is a from a from
Scholastic aquinus models of
psychology the chasm between the
fantasms and the intellectual activity
in Scholastic Traditions it's considered
a mystery they don't know what's
allowing the conversion of sense data
into the F What's called the fantasms
which I guess in core in this kind of
mapping logic would be the active States
uh there's no the explanation is kind of
obscured how you especially the problem
is our sense stum is on particulars a
particular dog or a particular
expression of light if you're looking at
in a room for example how do we do the
cognitional action of universals to get
the idea of this Quantum is in front of
me is the dog there's a whole thing
about that in
scholas atmology about that what's
relevant to this group is I'm a little
unconvinced that this argument of the
blanket is solving that problem I say
that because there what exactly is the C
like so if if if there's like three
variables that are basically being
interchanged with active States external
States sense States and internal States
you know obviously the correspondence of
the variables between active States and
external States and sense states to
internal States totally get it like I
could see how this Maps right uh but
between the variable X and
Mew what is that c like how is that
connected I'm not I didn't see anything
in the documents in the literature so in
this chapter so far to give that
explanation of how that conversion is
happening uh I might I may have Mis read
that I might completely be a mistake but
this is just in my mind I just know this
is a traditional uh problem in
epistemology of basically the
application of universals of perception
and cognitional activity there's a no
one really knows how to explain give an
account for that so that's why this
chapter caught my atttention and I'm a
little confuzzled about this uh because
eventually when he get drawn down to be
uh yeah unit U Bas of the variables
become U and Y when really mu and X are
seem to be the question mark of what
that is the thing of of translation uh
between the sense internal States and
the active external States how is that
happening I don't see that happening yet
um okay those those are just my
generally notes again I might be widely
wrong about this so I'm happy to be
corrected on that more strongly stated
second point but also that first point
on specifically the temporal nature of
of arrangement of generative hierarchies
and synchronicity coming in is a very
important factor I saw I read that I
actually have that down in my notes um
let's see what was
that yes that the internal states have
an appearance of representing external
States so mu dot is representing
appropriately x dot by the synchronicity
of the active uh state in the sense
statey and
do that's what I got thank you
thank you for the great comments so to
the second one first that's a very
perceptive comment which is that the um
particular
partition which is the starting point
for a free energy principle active
inference and not necessarily starting
point to get to any
phenomenological or metaphysical Point
potentially only as a starting point
just to do something empirical so first
a failure or a Delta to a philosophical
explanation may just be like a permanent
open question for a lot of other reasons
so the but but just to the kind of
philosophical implication part the edges
which represent what basically can
happen it's basically all the edges can
happen except for two kinds of things no
backwards
action no backwards perception but the
other arrows are like in principle
double-sided that doesn't mean in any
given situation they're like of equal
relevance also this is a map not a
territory so like just drawing a line
here between um you know the the the
North and the South side of the city
that that that line on the map is like
it's literally not describing what the
materiality is of the connection so
that's going to come back like again and
again obviously the map not ter
question so first category thing that
doesn't happen that reverse sensation I
don't have my thumb on the scale of
sensation or it's modeled like um part
of the sparsity of the models that it
just can't happen and the other thing
that can't happen is that action can't
be controlled externally action is under
um one the autonomous
control this is not like just pick it up
and pce it on to like an agent as
complex as a human because as we'll get
into like even in a tze we'll see how
limited it can be so this is just a
starting point of kind of like the the
like OnePlus One Lego block that then
more sophisticated models especially
with internal sophistication RS um but
the other kind of thing that doesn't
happen other than the backwards action
backwards sensation is the no telepathy
no no um telekinesis I guess like no no
communication from the outside except
through sensation no action effect on
the ex outside out except for through
action so that kind of gets this
question of like um how but isn't what
we actually care about the coupling
between the systems which is like the
The Edge that would connect these two I
think the um
[Music]
um it it's not with the Conor hind was
26 um basing Mechanics for stationary
proes that kind of comes back to this um
lrange
point this one talks about the blanket
so here's before partitioning the
blanket out
into um incoming sensory and outgoing
action so this is just the the um
initial marov blanket concept on an
undirected graph so both of these edges
are biral so this is kind of the simpler
version of
um this where the blank kit is broken
out into
two then um they study this the Locking
of the
mapping the actual stationarity in the
tracking is between the internal and the
external
state that is one that is the state St
it that is the kind of good regulator
like
stationarity so it captures both the um
intervention of the blanket
State and the I I'm I just don't
remember exactly which paper has the the
sigma
mapping between maybe someone else
remembers but the sigma mapping is is
the one that describes um
between the internal and the external
state so there is like it's like an
image or a map and it Maps between the
internal and external States but it's a
but it's a it's another um projection
but this only describes the causal uh
connections
Jeff yeah I just I just had a thought um
that I really haven't seen much in the
literature um until very recently about
Magneto
reception and also we know that we're
also sensitive to gravity but I haven't
really seen that modeled as a sense that
we actively participate in as well so
maybe there's something there when
you're talking about so-called
telekinesis um where where it's actually
just a natural phenomenon that that that
may be because we know for example Birds
right Birds navigate using the Earth's
magnetic field we know that um we know
that different different types of
animals have different sensitivity to
gravity fields we know that when for
example when we go Cuba Diving we lose
our sense of gravity right um so maybe
maybe that's just something to to just
stick in your your file cabinet I don't
know yeah definitely this live stream
from yesterday it was a rare Sunday live
stream like it it links to neurobiology
and a lot of other things and we we we
couldn't think of a linguistic example
that didn't
convey um that wasn't concordant with
like a gravitational
like metaphor being applied in a certain
way
Zach uh hi uh so can you say a little
bit about so there's no telekinesis yeah
but what if control over one specific
variable is in like one Markov blanket
and another is in another Markov blanket
would the separate Markov blankets under
some other hierarchical Markov blanket
be considered an external state or would
those all be inside of one big blanket
that you just call the set of internal
States if that makes
sense yeah
[Music]
um though in this like minimal form
they're labeled this
way they're all relative to each other
and that's all relative to the choice of
which one is chosen by the map drawer as
the internal state so it's not like
aspects of the world are like oh this
one's a sensory State now we can move on
it's like in this model where this is
the internal State and this is the
external State then they have this
directionality um there's an interesting
question I think it's in it's in chapter
two or three and it kind of highlights
how the uh textbook talks a lot about
generative model and generative
process but then
[Music]
um it has
Alli and then uh but more recently they
just described the entire statistical
model as the generative model so that's
the way that um many people talk about
generative modeling now that although
there are agents that are defined by
like the causal connections of the
blanket in the internal States so like
you can have agent based model as as you
could with net logo or any other kind of
modeling framework um there's no need to
talk about specific variables as being
intrinsically like an active state or a
sensory State because if it was like a
communication setting then the active
for one is the sensory of the other so
as soon as you're even in a a two agent
setting or anything that's um like
blurring the line with the basil
cognition or
anything you just build the program and
you use the structure the syntax of
the of the system that you're building
the model in like we can look at
pmdp and look at the code as it's kind
of rendered for some people that is
helpful to see that these are really
just variables that are defined in their
relationships
um and then when you start linking them
up they're they're they if you had
another you know extension it's was a
question that that we hav't and I don't
know if there's a specific total answer
which is like okay it's a wiring diagram
like this um and this was the kind of
core critique or or line of um inquiry
by this like how particular it's like
okay the FP has these
properties but does it retain those
properties like as you change the
topology of the ACT ction perception
Niche like if you don't have this double
edged Arrow or like like if you just had
Around the Clock like only one two 3
four what properties does that coupling
have can that one synchronize um across
the
blanket uh so I I I don't think it's
totally
resolved uh but it can be explored how
different connectivities
and of course different
parameterizations within a connectivity
relate to like different functions and
especially when getting into um internal
states that can have um Dynamic
structure so you'd say okay the
temperature in the room is going to just
be like it is what it is and then the um
thermometer and the air conditioner kind
of also are what they are but we have an
agent who can create higher order
abstractions about temperature through
structure alert so a lot of the change
happens like already blanketed off
from the sensory environment which I
think kind of touches on Thomas's Pro
problems questions
too awesome thank you so
much
pretty interesting
figure cool visualization could probably
be used more broadly or like something
like that like
some you using different colors and
types oh here's the mapping here's Sigma
mapping x y and
blanket so X and Y and then sense in
action let's
see past time
Point current time
point so here's just
describing the X maps
to action and itself internal
States our action selection and have
their own recurrent Dynamics and like
okay
analogously
two Sol little
coupling um I mean we can explore these
more in the paper I don't think this is
the same q but I think this reflects
that kind of like um kind of like lrange
Point like non-equilibrium steady state
something about how they're like in a
something like they're circulating in
some way
three is the blanket condition saying
it's this set composed of sense and
action summarized with this one node
and then the
assumptions some other kind of
conditional Independence like that they
all have this one other here they look
more
connected here's the sigma
mapping here's something else about this
observations or something pretty
cool I don't know how much more
graphical but but the category theory is
also taking it very graphically this is
still within the basian graph like
visualization approach but the category
Theory work probably has a lot of
visualization that that's also more
formal
argumentation any anyone else just any
other angle or we can go to some
questions also people can upvote the
questions but let's just look
at does anyone want to look at a
specific written one or new one or
should we just look at the most uploaded
ones Markov blanket explanation page 43
Box
31 so here's the
marov blanket in time
concept the or which is sometimes called
the marvian property like as has kind of
been discussed before the last names
don't really add any information because
there's like multiple marov and there's
multiple senses and all these things so
sometimes just using the descriptors
more informative but the marvian
Assumption like it just broadly in
statistics like talking about like a
Marian model or hidden marov model is
where the past time step influences the
next time step and then that influences
the future time step so the past only
influences the future through this kind
of retained One Step
present um how can this be
true it doesn't have to be a true fact
ontologically about a system it could
just be a a statistical approximation or
designed feature like a
program what if we don't know the
present
well that's a super broad
question by even sketching out like a
few nodes on a piece of paper or
thinking a little bit about a specific
system like what like what system not
knowing what about the
presence just sketching that out moves
along that question but the general form
is probably pretty big question they
Define markco blanket well they Define
it locally but it's
also prior defined the set of variables
that mediate all statistical
interactions between a system and
environment what's the statistical
rather than a non-statistical
interaction um here maybe in the broader
sense it's saying like it's about the
statistics of the map not the actual
territory so we're already in the domain
of statistics
another um way to read it would be like
it's kind of a probabilistic like across
like many similar or comparable
examples that it's not necessarily
seeking to give like for example a
mechanistic account or constructivist
account of how one thing happens it's
giving a
observational empirical numerical
approach to modeling like categories of
events
just like anyone would doing statistics
or AI or machine learning
Thomas kind blending questions one and
two together and what's the relationship
of hidden states with this because I
remember the model from the you know low
road Mo chapter there was a discussion
about hidden States being part of the
basically the calculation um so just
that question of not obviously the point
of not having all full information is
covered by the fact that there's hidden
states that are being accounted for uh
as I recall that from the chap on
chapter two in h in the low road process
so is that part of that relationship
here one of the ways to rec the connect
the two I
questions yeah like beliefs about hidden
states do come into play in the
variational free
energy and then also in prospective
planning and action selection like in
this book anytime you see X till the
um that's beliefs about hidden states
are always um more uncertain than
beliefs about
measurements so these two forms of
expected free
energy um expect like also always good
to just kind of like threshold that not
all things necessarily do this kind of
policy select ction process Like a Rock
doesn't have to be modeled with a policy
selection process or just a trivial one
but then getting into this like adaptive
action
setting then here's like the uncertainty
about how actions relate to World States
is always greater than uncertainty about
how actions map onto
observations best Cas they're equivalent
like in chess where there's a one toone
mapping between the um observation and
the hidden state of the piece on the
board that's like a fully observable
game not to say that the opponent's mind
is fully observable like but that's the
whole modeling um
process
uh those are maybe a few aspects of it
but what else what what what are the
kind of key aspects you think and how
maybe it's been approached
philosophically otherwise
like oh are you
ask or just like stat yeah kind of this
is a statistical model but not all
thinking on this issue has been
statistical so how just as kind of open
question but maybe if you have any
thoughts of any pre- statistical
thinkers and how they approach like
boundary I mean we normally argumented
by definition so the idea of an Essence
is defined by definition which is a
speci in general with the differential
basically combination um if you use mean
Plato in Theo talks about that using NE
necess necessary con property to Define
limit and thus used it to Define color
and figure and all that um so those are
non-statistical probabilities to
define basically some observation um in
fact actually from a more Norm like from
a more ethics normative point of view uh
the idea of examplars is the basically
exact opposite that the best
representation of reality is the
examplar versus uh an statistical
average right um so that would be kind
of the broadest kind of answer I've
agreed that broadest difference between
a statistical model and a
non-statistical is just use of
definition and Essence uh from a CL from
a traditional classic point of
view
cool really cool yeah that's awesome
thank you this is like the N equals one
and the
example and the a
priori
non-empirical and then the statistical
like or then the instrumental would kind
of which is just described basically
using it as a statistical model like
people often talk about this this is the
whole not the whole but the a lot of the
discussion around like do we do the
organism are they a generative model do
they have one are we just modeling it as
such that's this instrumentalism realism
question I mean if known claims are
being made about the territory then you
know one can always Retreat to just pure
map making but then there are stronger
guarantees of the once you've retreated
to map
making but then that has fundamentally
given up certain territory relating to
like how individual things
happen it's just and it's just a
different kind of it's a different kind
of
approach and and I I I know there's some
connections with the free frequentist
and the basian
statistics and like how do frequentists
view chance how does basian view chance
there's probably a lot to go in there
too yeah just to build on that just I
just by the way it wasn't like Aristotle
did not know about chance it was
discussed it's a know it was a known
thing the I think the big difference
just to CL I mean that's drawing on this
point is that
science ofis was supposed to be about
universals like this idea of kind of use
of chance to kind of observe and find
reality is that's the part where there
probably a huge Schism difference um
just from ran Point uh epistemology or
investigation there something different
so it was like they know they knew
chance existed and they definitely
acknowledged that certain things do
apply to that but it wouldn't be part of
a science it wouldn't be the mo the way
you would use to come to find the
universals is through random chance
yeah yeah and the role of abduction and
induction deduction and kind of which
ones are given what epistemic
statuses does anyone want to go to any
written question or or any new
one
here's no answer but this
lran again that's the last the last
names points like it's it's hard to know
is this lrange point it could be but it
might be totally unrelated it could be
different person different work or it
could be exactly the
same but like a point attractor or
something like that gives more
information okay let's
do let's just see how many from the
top trying to understand better how
figure 3.2 was produced EX exactly what
it
means okay so there are the variables
that are going to be used this is kind
of the simple blanket setting there's
going to be three variables X mu and B
so this is just in the undirected graph
setting before splitting out sense and
action
which is what kind of transposed it into
the cybernetics context but just one
blanket State um and then these are kind
of three projections down there's a cube
of statistical outcomes in the um like
variables taking on a number in the X Y
and Z Direction but it's in the X B and
mu
directions and then here are three
projections from the
cube on each of the faces down onto each
of the
faces um just comparing two different
variables um
so uh there's a positive relationship
between just a linear aggression between
X and
B and then you can condition on B like
you could kind of zero out like you
could talk about how many um standard
deviations each X was away from the
conditioned expectation on B so like
this one would be or this one would be
lower in standard
deviations than this
one just be it's like the residual from
the regression so there's just
statistical
methods and there's other relationships
that are drawn so these just describe
the like conditional dependencies like
kind of this this is like a statistical
Edge like but that is drawn that is
saying the scatter
plot has a a significant explanatory
power um but it's not exactly tested
like with a P value as such but just
saying that that's the slope is like the
the causal effect if the causal Edge
were one then all the points would just
be on a line like knowing one would be
like 100% like which is one in statistic
everything's kind of scaled to one
everything happens on the 0 to one
interval
Eric or Thomas and anyone
else got to follow up on basically my my
question about what what brings the what
pulls the X and mu value variable
together like this grap seems actually I
had that in my notes I forgot talk about
that right because what happens it looks
like it's using the blanket B to that's
the that third graph on the bottom left
is the combination right of the two V of
those two investigations or two
measurements and then that fourth graph
is the probability mapping of x
given uh look at the note yeah Pro given
the expected probability of mu given B
conditioned on mu I think best
understand to read
it yeah great that that that adds a lot
definitely so like
these two describe the conditional
dependencies between X and mu so
internal external States on blanket and
then here is that mapping so it's more
variable like let's just say that
there's a 08 relationship between the
temperature in the room and the
thermometer noisy thermometer 80% good
thermometer and then um there's a 8
Fidelity between me looking at the
numbers on the thermometer so just
coarsely it's like then there's going to
be a 64
relationship Sigma de facto like around
the
horn because of correlations amongst
variables so yet there's no direct
causal effect between the hidden State
and the the external State and the
internal state so that that describes
both like the the
intermediation and the kind of ultimate
correlation and so this is this is like
structural equation modeling is commonly
used like in population health or the um
earlier or it's oh it's in chapter four
here's like some some kind of here's one
hidden factor causing one observation
here's one here's lightning and then
here's the light part and the sound part
two observations from one underlying
State here's two causal factors that
combine to influence one
outcome these kinds of Bas and Gra iCal
methods are used like from like
knowledge database systems to health
modeling all these different kinds of
things okay if one defines these
preferred States as expected
States then one can say the living
organisms must minimize the surprise of
of their sensory
observations is it that preference is
the same as expectation or formally we
can use them in the same equation or
something
else does active inference make
ontological claims EG preference is
actually expectation just as heat is
actually exitation of molecules more
generally is a free energy principle
free energy in physics just an analogy
or is an ontological than
okay
okay one important thing to note is that
there's two senses of
expectation so in everyday usage the
meaning or the connotation is like what
we expect to happen like what what what
we expect will be the weather tomorrow
however also when we see the fancy e the
Big E expectation of or the sum of
something divided by n data points which
same as the the that's also called the
expectation also known as like the
central tendency or the mean so the
expectation of a distribution it's like
the expected returns but that's a
situation that's both about an uncertain
future moment and it has to do with the
moment with the central um tendency so
um it like it's just a statist even
within statistics those are just clear
based on the context or when what
variable um is coming to play um
inactive inference preferences so four
things that are choosing actions that
are using their that are exerting their
preferences let's look to
chapter seven so here's a model where
there's no preferences
involved that helped calibrate some of
these statistical questions about like
the prior the relationship between the
hidden State inference and the
observations through time through the a
matrix and like the B Matrix in how the
hidden state is inferred to change
through T but there's no action exerted
in this model but that brings out a lot
of these questions about like
observation hidden State how things
change in the world all these things
like that then that bottom structure is
still exactly the same and then here's
this action selection
part that invokes this variable C which
is called
preference it's not a reward function
it's a preference function that's a
distribution over
observations so it'll again come up in
um like chapter 7 and before what what
its structure is but this is one of the
core pieces of active inference models
that the preference component of the
action
selection which is going to come into
play in expected free energy in the
pragmatic value so this is going to
Define pragmatic value for that
variable that is defined in terms of
observations sensory
observations let's return return to the
question see if there was more to it but
that's kind of the key pece they're not
that preferences are not about future
points preferences come into they're not
using that future um unknown outcome
sense of
expectation but you could imagine a
planning agent that also has preferences
about future States or their preferences
right now C right now comes into
play in deciding action that matters for
future events
but
that's preferences over sensory outcomes
now having influence on action
selection not like a betting Market on
what an observation is going to be at a
future time Point per
se
so is preference the same as expectation
no but it'll be especially clear when
you just even sketch out a table or a
list of what is being described because
this is a very general this is like at
the level of definitions of
words formally we can use them in the
same equation there are situations where
it's an equation where you could
describe it in English using either of
those words but there's other situations
where you you couldn't so they're not
simply
swappable for that
reason this can't be really described
also I don't I don't know about this
heat is actually excitation molecules
kind of interesting metaphor but maybe
write more about it and then let's
explore it is free energy in physics
just an
analogy or is an ontological assertion
can analogies be ontological
assertions I don't know there's probably
a lot of things say on that question but
we'll go
on what's the difference between the
terms or does anyone have another in
like 10 10 minutes or we can just look
up like a few more of these or anyone
can ask or say anything
else
okay what's the difference between the
terms uh Thomas go for it hey sorry I
mean the the idea of the generative
model hierarchical generative models
based on time could we clarify that a
little bit more because it does sound
like um the fact of a hierarchy right
basically for example again the
classical model of a of a chain of being
that thing that uh entities have a
certain orological reality or hierarchy
right that rocks are not the same as
animals animals are not the same as
humans humans and God U there's a kind
of ontological hierarchy given on that
um of some orientation of how things are
arranged this chapter seems to talk
about the time duration as that ordering
property could you get more clarity that
or just like how strong of a statement
is that or what the implications are are
that yeah greate question okay few
pieces on this so um when you brought up
the first
time let's just say that we're going to
have planning over 100 years one kind of
model would be like a model where every
year from 1 to 100 is represented like
on a timeline or there could be a model
where there's 10 decades and then Each
decade has 10 points and so it's kind of
like you could have
um th thinner models that are nested
structurally so that like the tree
sweeps out all the possibilities
still and so there's multiple different
kinds of like hierarchical models that
could be built um you could have you
know 11s within a 20 within a 30 is like
that doesn't make sense maybe it's not
the most statistically optimal but
that's that's not outside the space of
statistical models that you can build
because these are just statistical
models however also people have gone I
think a lot further in arguing for like
time phenomenology
um an
example here's from 2018 an interview
with Carl friston from Alias um with
Martin
forer so there's a question about that
temporal
depth so we ask basically well you're
highlighting temporal depth a lot like
whether like thickness through time so
is it enough for a computer program to
do it and then if an ant colony is able
to persist over longer time scales than
other things like it then doesn't it
have more thickness to
[Music]
um it returns to this kind
of he brings up a lot of different
components and I think it it like kind
of remains to a very careful analysis
like which which claims he he brings out
to respond to it um because it
includes like questions about meta
awareness the depth of the model in
terms of the
counterfactuals like for example like um
use economic model the idea of of time
discounting for example and financial
modeling the idea that a $100 today has
more value than that
$100 10 years out because of properties
like inflation for example um so yeah
absolutely there's that kind of
self-referencing quality like kind of
Agents having self-awareness question
but also this this temporal time domain
has kind of external reality qualities
if we consider time preferencing
uh of value itself being a variable here
or being an area of
consideration yeah I think the deeper um
the the the deeper
philosophy is to be explored here's what
it looks like in the
code policy length equals
four that's the time depth of that agent
for time steps like that lets you
estimate how many um how big the policy
Vector is going to be if there's four
times uh if there's four um affordance
is or let's say five affordances like up
down left right and weight at each time
step then policy length of four is just
every sequence of those five affordances
so five to the
4th and then that's like tree search for
policy just like early chess algorithms
and then there's all these methods that
that are that are different but the
starting point is just like the model
defines the temporal depth of the
plan now what does this say about the
the actuality of time that's probably
pretty
open thank you yeah thank thank you for
the question yeah and and then like that
is what motivates all these okay well
now how about inference on policy length
and all these other things like it's
just about starting with a model
iterating with it seeing what phenomena
of the real system still AR are
unaccounted that that gets
far
okay in last minutes any
questions okay let's see so that was the
first discussion yeah Eric I'm sorry uh
this this might be a little
straightforward to some but whenever we
were talking about x dot whenever we
were talking about the Dynamics of
internal external as well as boundary
state
the dot did that mean with respect to
the derivative of the actual boundary uh
like variables or was that with respect
to time now now I'm kind of questioning
myself great
question if it's no explain it
explain oh I was just going to say if
that would take us over time we can uh
discuss it afterward in the uh
questions yes I I think at a first
reading the dot on these are the the
derivative of the variable so that the
value at when it's zero that is a
stationerity of that
variable so but the Dynamics of the
variable are defined in terms of a
function of those other states plus a
noise parameter which is what makes it
amenable to like all these kind of
stochastic calculus physics approaches
because this like separation into a
signal in a noise term on a flow is the
basis of a lot of other
formalisms and it's always hard to also
I think jump between this is like the
physics
formalism like physics of particular
systems flows L Gran all of that but
then when we're actually doing the
modeling in discret
setting it's like where's the marov
blanket
here because here it's just a partially
observable marov decision process but
people have had that for decades so
clearly they didn't need the particular
physics to do a PDP
so that's kind of an interesting thing
to explore
too okay next week at the later
time second part of
three otherwise in the other cohort
we're in chapter eight which is
continuous time models but seven is on
discreet
time so thank you all see you next
time bye